[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is the Madhyamini Kāyā, 75, to Magandiya.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus have I heard.
[SPEAKER_01]: On one occasion, the Blessed One was living in Puru country, where there was a town of the Kurus named Kama-sāma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kama-sāma.
[SPEAKER_01]: On a spread of grass, in the fire chamber of a Brahmin, belonging to the Bhara-vajra clan,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when it was morning, the Blessed One, dressed and taking His bowl and outer robe, went into Kama-sādāmal for alms.
[SPEAKER_01]: When He had wandered for alms in Kama-sādāmal and had returned from His own realm, after His meal, He went to a certain grove for the Days of Biding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having entered the grove, He sat down at the root of the tree for the Days of Biding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then the wanderer, Magandīya, while walking and wandering for exercise, went to the fire chamber of the brāhmaṇa belonging to the Bhāravāja clan.
[SPEAKER_01]: There he saw the spread of grass prepared and asked the brāhmaṇa, for whom has this spread of grass been prepared in the master Bhāravāja's fire chamber?
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems like it might be a recluse's bed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Master Magandya, there is a recluse Gautama, the son of the Satyans, who went forth from the Satyan clan.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now a good report of the Master Gautama has been spread to this effect.
[SPEAKER_01]: That blessed one is accomplished, fully enlightened, perfect in true knowledge and conduct, supplying nowhere of the world's incomparable leader of persons to be tamed, teacher of gods and humans, enlightened, blessed.
[SPEAKER_01]: This thread has been prepared for that Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_01]: Indeed, Master Parivaja, it is an ill sight we see when we see the bed of that destroyer of growth, Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_01]: Be careful what you say, Magandiya.
[SPEAKER_01]: Be careful what you say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many learned nobles, learned brahmins, learned householders, and learned recluses have full confidence in Master Gautama, and have been disciplined by him in a noble true way, in the dhamma that is also.
[SPEAKER_01]: Master Bharadwaja, even if we saw that Master Gautama face to face, we would tell him to his face.
[SPEAKER_01]: The reckless Gautama is a destroyer of growth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that has come down on our disciples.
[SPEAKER_01]: If Master Magandya has no objection, may I tell this to Master Gautama?
[SPEAKER_01]: Let Master Bharadwaja be at ease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tell him just what I have said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Meanwhile, with the divine ear, which is purified and surpasses the humour, the Blessed One heard this conversation between the Brahmin Bhāravāja and the wanderer Magandīva.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when it was evening, the Blessed One rose from meditation, went to the Brahmin's fire chamber and sat down on the spread of grass, made ready.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then the Brahmin Bhāravāja went to the Blessed One and exchanged greetings with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: When this courteous and amiable talk was finished, he sat down alongside.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Blessed One asked him, Paravājam, did you have any conversation with the wanderer Magandīya about this very same spread of grass?
[SPEAKER_01]: When this was said, the brāhmaṇa, awestruck and with his hair standing on end, replied, We wanted to tell Master Dottama about that very thing, but Master Dottama hasn't anticipated us.
[SPEAKER_01]: But this discussion between the Blessed One and the Brahman was left unfinished.
[SPEAKER_01]: For then the wanderer Magandir, while walking and wandering for eight sows, came to the Brahman's fire chamber and went up to the Blessed One.
[SPEAKER_01]: He exchanged greetings with the Blessed One, and when this courteous and amiable talk was finished, he sat down at one sow.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Blessed One said to him,
[SPEAKER_01]: Magandya, the I delights in forms, takes delights in forms, rejoices in forms.
[SPEAKER_01]: That has been tamed by the targeter, guarded, protected and restrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he teaches the dhamma for its restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Was it with reference to this that he said, the recluse Gotama is a destroyer of growth?
[SPEAKER_01]: It was referenced to this Master Gautama that I said, the rector's goal sign is the destroyer of ghosts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that is recorded when I spoke to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: The ear delights in sounds, the nose delights in odors, the tongue delights in flavors, the body delights in tangibles, the mind delights in mind objects, takes delight in mind objects, rejoices in mind objects,
[SPEAKER_01]: That has been tamed by the Tathāgata, guarded, protected and restrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he teaches the dhamma for its restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Was it with reference to this that you said, the reckless Gautama is a destroyer of growth?
[SPEAKER_01]: It was with reference to this Master Gautama that I said, the reckless Gautama is a destroyer of growth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that is recorded in our scriptures.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you think, Magandiya?
[SPEAKER_01]: Here, someone may have formerly enjoyed himself with forms cognizable by the eye, that are wished for, desired, agreeable and likable, connected with sensual desire and provocative of lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: On a later occasion, having understood as they actually are the origin, the disappearance and the gratification, the danger and the escape in the case of forms, he might abandon braving performance, remove fever performance, and abide without those with a mind inwardly at peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: What would you say to him, Magangwe?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing, Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_01]: Magandya formerly, when I lived the home life, I enjoyed myself, provided and endowed with five chords of sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: This form is cognizable by the eye, sounds cognizable by the ear, odors cognizable by the nose, the flavors cognizable by the tongue, the tangibles cognizable by the bodies that are wished for, desired, agreeable and likable, connected with sensual desire and provocative at last.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had three palaces, one for the rainy season, one for the winter, and one for the summer.
[SPEAKER_01]: I lived in the rains palace for the four months of the rainy season, enjoying myself with musicians, none of whom were men.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I did not go down to the lower palace.
[SPEAKER_01]: On a later occasion, having understood this, they actually are the origin, the disappearance, the gratification, the danger, and the escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the case of sensual pleasures, I abandoned craving for sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: I removed feeble for sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I abide without thirst, with the mind inwardly at peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see other beings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who are not free from lust for sensual pleasures?
[SPEAKER_01]: Beings devoured by craving for sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: Burning is the fever for sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: Indulging in sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I do not envy them, nor do I delight therein.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is, Magandiya, a delight apart from sensual pleasures, apart from unwholesome states, which surpasses even divine bliss.
[SPEAKER_01]: Since I take delight in that, I do not envy what is inferior, nor do I delight therein.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suppose Magandiya, a householder, or a householder's son, was rich with great wealth and property, and being provided and endowed with the five cords of sensual pleasure, he might enjoy himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: with forms cognizable by the eye, with sounds cognizable by the ear, with odors cognizable by the nose, with flavors cognizable by the tongue, with tangibles cognizable by the body, that are wished for, desired, agreeable, and likable, connected with sensual desire, and provocative of lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having conducted himself well in body, speech and mind, on the dissolution of the body, after death, he might reappear in a happy destination, in the heavenly world, in the retinue of the guards of the thirty-three.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there, surrounded by the group of nymphs, in a nandana grove, he would enjoy himself, provided and endowed with the five cords of divine sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suppose, then, he saw a householder, or a householder's son, enjoying himself, provided and endowed with the five cords of human sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you think Magandya?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would that young god, surrounded by the group of nymphsmen and undergrowth, enjoying himself, provided and endowed with the five cords of divine sensual pleasure, envy the householder for the five cords of human sensual pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or would he be enticed by human sensual pleasures?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why not?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because divine sensual pleasures are more excellent and sublime than human sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suppose Magandya, it was a leper with swords and blisters on his limbs, being devoured by worms, scratching off the scales,
[SPEAKER_01]: With his nails cauterizing his body over a burning charcoal pit, then his friends and companions, his kinsmen and relatives, would bring a physician to treat him.
[SPEAKER_01]: The physician would make medicine for him, and by means of that medicine, the man would be cured of his leprosy, and would become well and happy, independent, master of himself, able to go where he wants.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then he might see another leper, with sores and blisters,
[SPEAKER_01]: No, Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when there is sickness, there is need for medicine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when there is no sickness, there is no need for medicine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suppose Magandya there was a leper with swords and blisters on his limbs, being devoured by worms, scratching the scabs off the openings of his wounds with his nails, cauterizing his body over a burning charcoal pit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then his friends and companions, his kinsmen and relatives, brought a physician to treat him.
[SPEAKER_01]: The physician would make medicine for him, and by means of that medicine, that man would be cured of his leprosy, and would become well and happy, independent, master of himself, able to go where he likes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then two strong men would seize him by both arms, and drag him towards a burning charcoal pit.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you think, Magandya?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would that man twist his body this way and that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that fire is indeed painful to touch, hot and scorching.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you think, Madandya?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it only now that the fire is painful to touch, hot and scorching?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or previously, too, was that fire painful to touch, hot and scorching?
[SPEAKER_01]: Master Gautama, that fire is now painful to touch, hot and scorching.
[SPEAKER_01]: And previously, too, that fire was painful to touch, hot and scorching.
[SPEAKER_01]: For when that man was a leper, with sores and blisters on his limbs, being devoured by worms, scratching the scaffold openings of his wounds with his nails, his faculties were impaired.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, though the fire was actually painful to touch, he acquired a mistaken perception of it as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So too, Magandya, in the past, sensual pleasures were painful to touch, hot and scorching.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the future, sensual pleasures will be painful to touch, hot and scorching.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, at present, sensual pleasures are painful to touch, hot and scorching.
[SPEAKER_01]: But these beings who are not free from lust for sensual pleasures, who are devoured by craving for sensual pleasures, who burn with a fever for sensual pleasures, have faculties that are impaired.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, those sensual pleasures are actually painful to touch.
[SPEAKER_01]: They acquire a mistaken perception of them as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that note, that's what I was saying yesterday, when you spoke, when I was explaining that
[SPEAKER_00]: When people initially start practicing the restraint, they might feel, like, pangs, pain in regard to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: They see something with their eye, something pleasant, something with their ear, or with their tongue, and it could be assumed that that pain was because of the restraint placed upon the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: But actually, if one sticks to the strength and doesn't give in to the senses, it becomes apparent that that pang is the very nature of the senses, of the sensual pull, of the sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means that pang was always there, it just was never felt, because it was never resisted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because one just went with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in order to not feel the pain of that dart,
[SPEAKER_00]: You just quickly succumb, quickly say yes, so it doesn't hurt you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the simile I gave yesterday, I think, we didn't record it, but was, like, imagine you have a very, very strong dog on the leash, and something comes in its eyesight, and you see it's beginning to run for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you know the dog is powerful and if you stay in the place where you were, it's just going to rip your arms and it's going to be very unpleasant and very painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just start running with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, obviously, you develop all sorts of views on on account of enjoying the run or whatever else, when in reality, you really have no choice but going with the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because saying no to it is just dreadful.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can terrify people and make them freak out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why sometimes when the circumstances place the restraint on you, so to speak, when you can't get what you want, it drives people mad.
[SPEAKER_00]: That pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, even from the day one, when somebody starts practicing the restraint, the pain of restraint, it's not caused by the restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's revealed by the restraint and that is the pain of the senseless and sensual force.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what the Buddha is saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: All this, even when you were enjoying the senses in the past, and all those people who will enjoy them in the future, those sensual pleasures are actually painful, like that fire that was always painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, only the mind that is impaired in regard to that nature, would blame the pain to, like, lack of satisfaction of your senses, not the lack of actually understanding of the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, when people feel pain on a tantra senses, they think it's because they haven't indulged them enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: They blame the restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's completely the other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the actual delight and lust, it's the dark that affects you, that it's so unpleasant, that you kind of automatically just go for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go for the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, not just that you mask, cover up the dirt, but then you also get the pleasure that's kind of contained in the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then you feel like you win both ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: You feel like you avoid the pain, and you feel like you enjoy the pleasure on top of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact is that that is not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, fundamentally, it is optional, but for most people, it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're just too weak to say no to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that they're always driven by it, means, basically, they're always slaves to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is no pleasure at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't see the actual fever, the burning.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: They blame the fever, the burning, to the lack of satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then they just think, I just have to go harder for it, until the fever, the burning disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just cover it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you pursuing the desire more, does not make the fever and burning disappear, makes it increase, makes it burn even harder next time, which is going to make you run for it even harder, as a result.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, the whole kind of... the only thing you're going to accomplish is cover up, cover up all the same burning embers.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about burning... well... like the Nepalese, it just has to be... charcoal, a bit of close burning spoons.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the pain of the sense desire that's revealed by the restraint, I'm just repeating that, is, belongs to the sense desire, not the restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: The restraint merely reveals it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, the restraint is the necessary precondition for arising of wisdom, for arising of the understanding of the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But with like, if you, if you restrain yourself, you still have the, that pull.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, the pain with the senses is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're not going further and getting more, you know, feverish.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the pain, the pain will be there for as long as it doesn't sink deep enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the pain does not belong to restraint, it belongs to the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for that very reason, the restraint is actually quite pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fire will always be hot, even a hundred miles away from you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now that you're not pulled towards it, and you know there is no danger of you falling into that burning pit, here it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of your restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't go anywhere near it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence the pleasure of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always trumps the pleasure of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the pleasure of sensuality is always very valuable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But your mind will go everywhere else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Away from that central pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like that man who was being dragged by the two stronger men to the pit, he would want to be everywhere else but that pit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you recognize that the whole pain, the whole kind of drama and proliferation and everything and mess that comes with it, it's all on account of the central pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all you have to do is say no to it and you're literally free from that entire domain of misfortune.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then there was another sutra where the Buddha did say all the... fathers fight with sons, sons fight with mothers, brothers with sisters, brothers with brothers, kings with kings, nations with nations, all on account of sensual pleasures, all on account of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of the wars that are being waged, that will be waged, it's all on account of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing works.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's... it's... all of that might not mean anything if a person on that individual, private, personal level, still don't recognize the pain of sensuality belonging to the actual sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the pain of saying no to sensuality, belonging to the actual sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not to you saying no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Saying no, merely reveals it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suppose, Magandya, there was a leper with sores and blisters on his limbs, being devoured by worms.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, the more you cover it up, the more you'll need to cover it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the more you'll assume that covering up is sorting it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you will get some satisfaction in pursuing desire, because, basically, it makes you forget about the pain caused by the very desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it's become a more delusional... Because that's all it can do, make you forget about the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you can never satisfy a desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: In its nature, it's insatiable.
[SPEAKER_00]: For the very reason that all you can do is forget about the pain, the pang, the dart that it causes to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why people like to elaborate on their desires, not just go and satisfy them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it provides a more elaborate, forgetful cover-up of the of the actual pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: But only so for that dart to arise again, to hit you again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when your senses do break apart, when you can't use any of those domains for this game of cover-up, then you're just left with the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why old age can be very hard for those who depend on their senses more than others.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dhamma continues.
[SPEAKER_01]: So too, Magandhiya, beings who are not thief and lust for sensual pleasures, who are devoured by craving for sensual pleasures, who burn with the fever for sensual pleasures, still indulge in sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more such beings indulge in sensual pleasures, the more their craving for sensual pleasures increases, and the more they are burned with their fever for sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, they find a certain measure of satisfaction and enjoyment, independent from the fire called sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you think, Magandhiya?
[SPEAKER_01]: Have you ever seen or heard of a king or a king's minister enjoying himself, provided and endowed with the five codes of sensual pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Who, without abandoning, craving for sensual pleasures, without removing fever for sensual pleasures, was able to abide free from thirst, with a mind inwardly at peace?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or who is able, or who will be able to abide, to so abide?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, Master Gautam.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good, Vagandhīr, I too have never seen or heard of a king or a king's minister enjoying himself without abandoning craving for sensual pleasures, without removing fever for sensual pleasures, who is able to abide free from thirst with the mind inwardly at peace, or who is, who is able, or who will be able to so abide.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the contrary, Magandhiya, those recluses of Rāmas who abided, or abide, or will abide, free from thirst, with the mind inwardly at peace, all do so after having understood, as they actually are, the origin, the disappearance, the gratification, the danger, and the escape in the case of sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it is after abandoning, craving for sensual pleasures, and removing people from sensual pleasures, that they are guided, or abide, or will abide, freedom first, with a mind inwardly of peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, at that point, the Blessed One uttered these exclamations.
[SPEAKER_01]: The greatest of all games is health.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nibbāna is the greatest bliss.
[SPEAKER_01]: The eightfold path is the best of paths, for it leads safely to the deathless.
[SPEAKER_01]: When this was said, the wanderer Magandiya said to the Blessed One, It is wonderful, Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is marvelous how well that has been expressed by Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_01]: The greatest of all gains is health.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nibbāna is the greatest bliss.
[SPEAKER_01]: We, too, have heard earlier Wanderers, who were teachers of teachers, saying this, and in degrees with Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, Magandiya, when you heard earlier Wanderers, who were teachers and teachers of teachers, saying this, what is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is that health?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is that nibbāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: When this was said, the wanderer Magandya rubbed his own limb with his hands and said, This is that health, Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is that nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: For I am now healthy and happy, and nothing afflicts me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, bless it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He goes on with the simile.
[SPEAKER_01]: Magandya, suppose there was a man born blind who could not see dark and light forms, who could not see blue, yellow, red or pink forms, who could not see what was even and uneven.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might hear a man with good eyesight say, Then he would go in search of a white cloth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then a man would cheat him with a dirty soiled garment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, Good man, here is a white cloth for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Beautiful, spotless and clean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, he would accept it and put it on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, being satisfied with it, he would utter words of satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, good indeed, sirs, is a white cloth, beautiful, spotless and clean.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you think, Magandib, when that man, born blind, accepted that dirty soil of the garment, put it on, and, being satisfied with it, uttered words of satisfaction thus?
[SPEAKER_01]: Good indeed, sirs, is a white cloth, beautiful, spotless, and clean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did he do so knowing and seeing, or out of faith in a man with good eyesight?
[SPEAKER_01]: Venerable sir, he would have done so unknowing and unseen, out of faith in a man with good eyesight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So too, Magandha, the wanderers of other sects, are blind in visions.
[SPEAKER_01]: They do not know health.
[SPEAKER_01]: They do not see Nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet they utter this stanza thus.
[SPEAKER_01]: The greatest of all games is health.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nibbāna is the greatest bliss.
[SPEAKER_01]: This stanza was uttered by the earlier accomplished ones, fully enlightened ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, the greatest of all gains is health.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nibbāna is the greatest bliss.
[SPEAKER_01]: The eightfold path is the best of paths, for it leads to Saipu, to the Vyāsas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now it has gradually become current among ordinary people.
[SPEAKER_01]: And although this body, Magandhya, is a disease, a tumor, a dart, a calamity, and an affliction, referring to this body, you say, this is that health, Master Gautama, this is that nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You do not have that noble vision, Magandhya, by means of which you might know of and see nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have confidence in Master Gautama thus.
[SPEAKER_01]: Master Gautama is capable of teaching me the dhamma in such a way that I can come to know health and to see nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: In Uganda, suppose there was a man born blind who could not see dark and light forms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then his friends and companions, his kinsmen and relatives, would bring a physician to treat him.
[SPEAKER_01]: The physician would make a medicine for him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, by means of that medicine, the man's vision would not arise or be purified.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you think, Magandya?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would the doctor reap weariness and disappointment?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_01]: So too, Magandya, if I were to teach you the dhamma thus, this is that help, this is that nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might not know that help or see nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that would be worrisome and troublesome for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have confidence in Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_01]: Master Gautama is capable of teaching me the dhamma in such a way that I can come to know health and seem reborn.
[SPEAKER_01]: Magandya, suppose there was a man born blind who could not see dark and light forms.
[SPEAKER_01]: He might hear a man with good eyes saying, Good indeed, sirs, is a white cloth, beautiful, spotless and clean.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he would go in search of a white cloth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then a man would cheat him with a dirty soiled garment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, a good man hears a white cloth, and he would accept it and put it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And his friends and companions would bring a physician to treat him.
[SPEAKER_01]: The physician would make medicine,
[SPEAKER_01]: Ointments and counter-ointments, nasal treatments, and by means of that medicine, the man's vision would arise and be purified.
[SPEAKER_01]: Together with the arising of his vision, his desire and liking for that dirty soiled garment would be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then he might burn with indignation and ill will towards that man and might think that he ought to be killed thus.
[SPEAKER_01]: Indeed, I've long been tricked and treated, and defrauded by this man's, these dirty soiled garments, when he told me, good man, here's a white cloth, blue, beautiful, spotless and clean.
[SPEAKER_01]: So to Magandiya, if I were to teach you the dhamma, this, this is that health, this is that nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might know health and see nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Together with the arising of your vision, your desire and lust for the five aggregates affected by assumption might be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, perhaps, you might think, indeed, I have been long tricked and cheated and defrauded by this mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: For when assumption, I have... when assuming, I have been assuming just to material form.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have been assuming just to feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have been assuming just to perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have been assuming just to determinations.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have been assuming just to consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: With my assumption as condition, being comes to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: With being as condition, birth.
[SPEAKER_01]: With birth as condition, aging and death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, grief and despair come to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Such is the origin of this wholeness of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have confidence in Master Gautama thus.
[SPEAKER_01]: Master Gautama is capable of teaching me the dhamma in such a way that I might rise up from the seat cured of my blindness.
[SPEAKER_01]: associate with true men.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you associate with true men, you will hear the true dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you hear the true dhamma, you will practice in accordance with the true dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you practice in accordance with the true dhamma, you will know and see for yourself thus.
[SPEAKER_01]: These are diseases, tumours and darts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But here, these diseases, tumours and darts cease without remainder.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the cessation of my assumption comes cessation of being.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the cessation of being, cessation of birth.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the cessation of birth, ageing and death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, grief and despair cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Such is the cessation with the whole, this whole mess of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: When this was said, the Wanderer Magandhiya said, Magnificent Master Gautama, magnificent!
[SPEAKER_01]: Master Gautama has made the dhamma clear in many ways, as though he were turning upright, or had been overthrown, revealing what was hidden, showing the way to one who was lost, or holding up a lamp in the dark for those with eyesight to see forms.
[SPEAKER_01]: I go to Master Gautama for refuge of the dhamma, and to the Saṅgha of Bhikkhus.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would receive the going forth under the Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would receive the full admission.
[SPEAKER_01]: Magandiya, one who formerly belonged to the other sect and desires the going forth on full admission in this dhamma and discipline, lives on probation for four months.
[SPEAKER_01]: At the end of the four months, if the bhikkhus are satisfied with him, they give him the going forth on full admission to the bhikkhu state.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I recognize individual differences in this matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Venerable Sir, if those who formerly belonged to another sect and desire the going forth and full mission in its dhamma and discipline, live on probation for four months,
[SPEAKER_01]: And, if at the end of the four months the bhikkhu is being satisfied with them, give them the going forth and full admission to the bhikkhu state, then I will live on probation for four years.
[SPEAKER_01]: At the end of four years, if the bhikkhus are satisfied with me, let them give me the going forth and full admission to the bhikkhu state.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then the wanderer Magandiya received the going forth under the Blessed One, and he received the full admission.
[SPEAKER_01]: And soon, not long after his full admission, dwelling alone, withdrawn, diligent, ardent and resolute, the Venerable Magandīr, by realizing for himself, with direct knowledge, here and now, entered upon and abided in that supreme goal of the holy life, for the sake of which clansmen rightly go forth, from the home life into homelessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: He directly knew, birth is destroyed, the holy light has been lived, what had to be done has been done.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no more coming to any state of being.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Venerable Magandya became one of the elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I like the fact that he wasn't
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, he was determined.
[SPEAKER_01]: It didn't really matter if he went forth, if he was still going to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He listened to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He'd take on the Buddhist teaching and go for it, no matter how long it took.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he doesn't want to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Going forth is just an external means, a statement, a livelihood and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, for somebody who's been feeling this through the dhamma back, right there and then,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Four months, four years, doesn't matter, because you'll be doing the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be practicing, withdraw, renunciation, dwelling resolute.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, resolute.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're basically dwelling resolute.
[SPEAKER_00]: One thing is to understand, but another thing is to stick to it, for as long as it is necessary, for all of the assumptions and habits of desires, fame.
[SPEAKER_00]: For some people, it will take longer.
[SPEAKER_00]: For some people, it will take shorter time.
[SPEAKER_01]: But without being resolute.
[SPEAKER_00]: But exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Resolution needs to be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, resolution is possible only once understanding has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't know what you're supposed to be resolute about, well, then all the resolution in the world won't help you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what about restraint, if you say, never again?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But obviously, again, never again might free, if they stick to it, might free people from sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's still not necessarily... doesn't mean that they will have the right view in terms of dhamma and nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the Buddha did say, even the two-year-old can experience this passion and this thirst in regard to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And free himself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he can't free himself from other assumptions, assumptions of self, of conceit, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But obviously, it would be much easier for somebody who's free from sensuality to then understand the dhamma, than from somebody who isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he already kind of understood the principle of assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just needs to be pointed out, that very fact, that padāna, of sensual pleasures, of craving, has been obviously abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he needs to dwell on the nature of that abandonment, and then apply the same to the sense of self, and his conceit, and then he'll be in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: But obviously, he can't do that unless he's... somebody points that out to him, somebody who knows.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, to me also, resolute means you don't take... you see the goal, you take nothing less than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what you're striving for.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, resolution can be basically... can take many forms.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be resolute for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any, any, any sensual pleasure that comes within the range of your senses, you will basically override with a vision of pain, and dirt, and burning embers.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's how they actually are.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might not necessarily see that, but you took it of faith, because the Buddha said it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you keep applying it, because it is so, it will take its roots, and then you will see itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, you can take on faith wrong instruction and then no amount of applying it will result in seeing it clearly as such, because it's not as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sensuality is as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you kind of emulate in seeing it as such, like overriding with your resolution, will result in eventually seeing it for what it is, as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's basically those people who practice on faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: They take on faith and they just stick to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, it's been made pretty clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I don't think, like, you know, if there is a resolution, if there is a restraint, if there is a virtue established, I don't think it will take too long for one to start seeing that actually they are painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't be before too long before it becomes apparent that the pain of restraint is not of restraint, but it's revealed by restraint and it's of the senses, of the desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the first point of contact.
[SPEAKER_00]: Make sense?
[SPEAKER_00]: Something like with the essential pleasure, first point of contact is pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything else, all the pleasure you then get from giving in to those desires, is built on top of those burning embers.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means they themselves are certainly not pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: The origin of sensual pleasures?
[SPEAKER_01]: The origin of their arising?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the arising of sensual pleasure, basically, would... you can pin down on your assumption of... in regard to sensual pleasure, your assumption that they were unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, you will crave for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And craving for them will then make them, make you regard them as even more pleasant, and so on, feed itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop craving for them, sensuality cannot arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Agreeable, beautiful objects in the world will still arise, but they, they will not induce sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you recognize that sensuality, like beautiful sights, for example, are confined to the domain of sight, to the eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is a sensual desire to see something beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you say no to it, you will experience pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what the desire is, pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And people don't experience pain, because their minds are already far out in the anticipation of satisfaction and desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're already running, even before the dog started yanking them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But all you have to do is just stop, and the pain will arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, as I said, with some instruction, and diligence, and resolve it, but if you become a parent,
[SPEAKER_00]: That pain, no matter like big or small sometimes, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the pain of the actual sensual touch.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the pain of craving present simultaneously with an agreeable beautiful object in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, you remove the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what you have is just beautiful objects in the world, but no desire for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that brings you to the, well, other approach, the approach of Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_00]: With dhamma, with craving, suffering is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whenever there is pain, there is craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you suffer on account of sensuality, it's because you crave.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality is craving for sense-objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: That, as a whole, as a kind of, as a unit, that's what sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving for sense-objects, or pleasures derived through the sense-objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you can rightly say, sensuality is painful and unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can't have sensuality, then, without the main component of craving for the sense-objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's seen a danger of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: We see the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is pain, there is suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger of craving, basically, like... Craving for pleasure derived from sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, sense objects cannot be discerned if there are no operating, functional, living, healthy senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's something that's completely obscured.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as I said, the mind is already out there with the actual pleasures that you derive from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you took everything that precedes those pleasures, you took that for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: You made it be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhāva is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensual being is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind is far.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, as I said, for example, if your mind is fully dependent on the pleasures derived by the sense base and sense objects, if something happens to sense bases and sense objects, and something will happen because they're not in your control, then the mind will be cut away with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is what death is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're being swept with the floods that sweep away your body, your five senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, unless you climb down that tree, those sense trees, on the safe ground, when they're taken down, you will crash with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that is the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a real danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what death is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Death cannot touch you, if your mind is withdrawn from the dependence on the pleasure of the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, somebody just... all you have to do is just contemplate losing your sight, losing your ears, losing your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, like, say there is an imminent danger of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: No amount of sense desire will override that, no matter how strong it was before.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that the very next second you might be dead, you will drop everything you were doing, everything you want to do, everything you were engaged with.
[SPEAKER_00]: And most likely, a normal person would freak out then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Become religious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or become religious, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Start praying to the Divine Providence and develop a faith that everything will end up well for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically the whole purpose of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, it's the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: It emulates the principle of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were hit by the pain, you cover it up with a pleasant desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were hit by the pain of non-sensual nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cover it up with the assumptions of everything will be fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, pleasure, peaceful, it's okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the whole purpose of human religiousness and superstition is a cover-up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just extension of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, it's another type of upādāna, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sīla Bhātraparamāsa.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, belief, assuming, holding on to virtues, duties, extension into religion and so on, holding on to views, assuming the views, that's also comes on brain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's a bit to know what, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the greatest of happiness in most people is a fully functional, vastly strong body that can take you around and get all those pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like the peak of happiness that you can imagine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is simultaneously the peak of the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means like that's when your dependence, your blind dependence, like you're not aware of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're too far out with the expectations of pleasures, that's with the dependence in its full highest swing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because a person might start withdrawing from the central pleasures when senses start failing.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, if you wait for your senses to start failing, and then withdraw, well, you are not withdrawing, you are being withdrawn.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, what you're going to have, then you're going to have views, and all sorts of assumptions based on that, that now you cannot undo.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's kind of too late, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your dependence on it has been fortified.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you think you're at old age,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the danger of old age, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, theoretically, it's still possible to uproot it all and become an arahant, but highly unlikely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, I mean, the habit of dependence on the senses has been cultivated many fold, much longer than for somebody who was 20 or 30 years old.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means all sorts of views and assumptions on top of that have arisen, and now the senses have, you know, declined.
[SPEAKER_00]: And sure, your ability to kind of experience the central pleasure has declined, but not the assumption of the pleasures of the senses and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That has stayed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now you have no kind of reference point for that to undo it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When your senses were still there, you could see a direct link, direct dependence on your assumptions upon the central pleasures and everything else, and the actual operating senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, the senses are gone, and you're so oblivious in regard to them, ignorant, deluded, indolent, it's virtually impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Theoretically, it's possible, but highly unlikely.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the longer you wait...
[SPEAKER_00]: I would have said that, actually, in that sutta, you just read it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The longer you engage with sensuality, the stronger it gets.
[SPEAKER_00]: The more dependent upon you become.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means the more painful it will be, saying no to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, the greater pain will be revealed by saying no to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And mind cannot take the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Untrained mind cannot take the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what will untrained mind, which cannot take the pain, do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Try to avoid the pain, but it only means that you know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means of survival.
[SPEAKER_00]: You end up revolving around that which causes you pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're using that to avoid that pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what about you can wean yourself off of sensual pleasures?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you can't do that either.
[SPEAKER_01]: But just a little bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I used to have a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha said, in regard to the being, and there is a being of sensual pleasures as well, he said basically that as much as a large lump of excrements stinks, even the small bits of excrements share the same stink.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same foul smell.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same goes for the being of any kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same goes for sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, weaning yourself of excrement, with little excrement, is not weaning yourself of excrement smell at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: The excrement smell is still present.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter the amount of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: How big the lung is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for example, that someone is doing something innocent enough, you know, not so bad, it's still a distraction, like watching movies.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, watching movies, distracting yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, it's not a horrible thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're watching action movies or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the person sees, okay, well, that's distracting, that's got nothing to do with dhamma, it's got nothing to do with holy love.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, I'll watch something with... it's got a... you know, connected to dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dhamma movie.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eh, well, there is no such a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then I... well, connected to old age and death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, I'm weaning myself of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but see, the point is, you turn a blind eye to the fact that the purpose of a movie is... sorry, the purpose of the movies, in general, is entertainment.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's taking your mind away.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that taking your mind away, it's nothing other than moha, the delusion, the indolence of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I was saying yesterday, delusion is... it's not... it's not a kind of a hidden secret truth that you are not aware of.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are deluded.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Delusion is an attitude of mind, in the same sense, anger is and lust is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's lust aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sure, you might watch a dhamma movie that does not have the explicit sensuality, provocativeness, and so on, but the fact is that you're engaging in the indolence of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: You let your mind go where the movie is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let the story unfold.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take your mind on a ride, which is not necessarily sensual ride, but it's the ride of the vision.
[SPEAKER_00]: The ride of indolence, which is basically that which is kind of undermining, sorry, underlying both
[SPEAKER_00]: Lust and anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your mind is never indolent, it cannot give in to lust nor anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you are practicing delusion, basically, if you're practicing indolence, means you remain liable to lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remain accessible to lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lust remains possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sure, you can watch all sorts of documentaries and informative movies and whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact is, your mind goes in a state of indolence, which means when the lust comes, you will not be fortified in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is no excuse for this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, non-indolence is just...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you remain non-indolent, you will not give in to any distraction, no matter how informative the inverted comma is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because dhamma is to be known individually, internally, by the wise, not on a big screen.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if it's the movie about the Buddha's life, again, it could be watched as distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the only way to remain mindful of a movie is to basically not give in to the movie.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that means, why watch it in the first place?
[SPEAKER_00]: Same like reading novels or books of any kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're meant to take the mind away.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not as bad as, you know, full-on pursuit of sensuality, you know, in a binging manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's certainly maintaining the indolence of the mind, maintaining the delusion, maintaining the ignoring.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's an important point, because many people still have notions and assumptions that delusion and even avijja, it's kind of, you know, this metaphysical ignorance that is then revealed by some extraordinary transcendental experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's something you engage most often.
[SPEAKER_00]: More often than sensuality, more often than anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what avijjā is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what delusion is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's indolence of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's muddleness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lack of clarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you maintain that.
[SPEAKER_00]: People maintain that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You maintain it through sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: You maintain it through anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: You maintain it through ignorant choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: You maintain it through distraction and dependence on distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you remove a distraction from... Well, remove all of the distractions from a normal person out there in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they'll freak out.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, the boredom will start creeping in, and then the boredom will reveal a terror behind it.
[SPEAKER_00]: A real genuine fear of, and a threat, a real genuine threat of sinking into your own mind, and drowning there, where man lives.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, quickly, provide with some distractions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Give me something to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it's devoted to waitfulness, it's saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, it sounds nice, like, you know, it's a, it's quite a heavy thing to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a heavy thing to do initially, but until you, until you still have the pull of the senses and so on, it feels like a heavy work.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it is, it is a heavy work initially.
[SPEAKER_00]: As we spoke in, was a couple of days ago,
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a herdsman looking after the cows.
[SPEAKER_00]: While the cows are still wild and unrestrained, it's going to be a lot of work to keep them away from the paddy field, from eating other people's crop.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once they have tamed and calmed down, then it's just pure pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just sit.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't even have to move.
[SPEAKER_01]: They listen to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't go.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, initially, for a person who never practiced wakefulness, it's going to be the hardest task in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's devoted to awakening.
[SPEAKER_01]: This means less sleeping.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means less sleep even when you're awake.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means less distractions.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means not resting mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean you're fully engaged in constant effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means you're engaged in non-resting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the simile of a cow, that if it sits down, it's being eaten by the animals, devoured by the animals that live on the ground.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it leans on something, stands up and leans on something, it's devoured by the animals that live on the things, on the trees, it leans and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, no position of the mind, you give in to that kind of, ah, just to rest for five minutes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can rest your body all you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: And shut it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But mind, exactly, no shutting up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because actually, shutting off is not necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why delusion is a habit.
[SPEAKER_00]: A vijja is a habit that's being maintained through a vijja.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance is determined by ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Nibbāna mentions it as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the point is, once the mind is trained in wakefulness, wakefulness is effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it ceases to be a chore.
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes a very pleasant, peaceful abiding.
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, obviously, yeah, the pull to go back to Avijjā is the... Well, as long as Avijjā is not entirely uprooted, exactly, Avijjā will try to maintain itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the same sense, basically, that a person sees danger in sensuality, sees it as burning embers, so should the indolence of the mind be seen as well, non-wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is, what I said, the ones who are not mindful are already as if dead.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, living is quite difficult.
[SPEAKER_01]: Real living, in that case.
[SPEAKER_00]: Real living is a full-time task.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's again what Nyanavila Therese said.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not some... Life is not something you just float and fly over and go through.
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes actually full-time task.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even for the one who is not necessarily practicing for Arahantship, just wants to live authentically, wants to live responsibly, wants to live mindfully.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it is that anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if for a patujana, a sutta patujana, uninstructed, without any regard, it's also... it's even worse, because he's making it worse through ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's making his itch worse through constantly scratching it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's making it powerful each time, which means each time he'll need to work even harder to undo it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can never have too much of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you have too much of anything else, mindfulness will even it out, if mindfulness is established.
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarity of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-muddledness, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Clear thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: And restraint in the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, even a very little of the instruction from the suttas and the buddha will be required, because the ground is very fertile, set up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything is there, ready, in the right order, purified.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you need very little instruction to fix it up, once and for all.